<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: William it was really nothing…</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/freelyassociating/2009/02/william-it-was-really-nothing/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2009/02/william-it-was-really-nothing/</link>
	<description>THE FREE ASSOCIATION</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 11:17:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: david</title>
		<link>/2009/02/william-it-was-really-nothing/#comment-1479</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[david]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2009 15:37:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=246#comment-1479</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It&#039;s not easy to escape from all this good stuff about temporalities. In my becoming-father persona, I&#039;ve started reading &lt;em&gt;Birth without Violence&lt;/em&gt;, by Frederick Leboyer. This is from the translator&#039;s preface:

&lt;blockquote&gt;To be born and to give birth are one and the same; that the very act of giving birth takes a woman back to the moment of her own birth. This new perception of time, of finding oneself outside the limits of time as we know it, can be very confusing. One becomes award that giving birth takes place in an altered state of consciousness. Birth, death, dying, being born or giving birth -- nearly all merge at times, all become the same adventure into and out of that territory we might call no-man&#039;s-land.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s not easy to escape from all this good stuff about temporalities. In my becoming-father persona, I&#8217;ve started reading <em>Birth without Violence</em>, by Frederick Leboyer. This is from the translator&#8217;s preface:</p>
<blockquote><p>To be born and to give birth are one and the same; that the very act of giving birth takes a woman back to the moment of her own birth. This new perception of time, of finding oneself outside the limits of time as we know it, can be very confusing. One becomes award that giving birth takes place in an altered state of consciousness. Birth, death, dying, being born or giving birth &#8212; nearly all merge at times, all become the same adventure into and out of that territory we might call no-man&#8217;s-land.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
