<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: On the uses of fairy dust</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/freelyassociating/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/</link>
	<description>THE FREE ASSOCIATION</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 11:17:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: Are these scandals the symptoms of a Zombie? &#124; freely associating</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1678</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Are these scandals the symptoms of a Zombie? &#124; freely associating]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2011 13:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1678</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[[...] of contemporary policing and politics must be taken into account in any new invocation of the fairy dust that can spark social movements. But left on its own it is just as likely to collapse back into the [...]]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] of contemporary policing and politics must be taken into account in any new invocation of the fairy dust that can spark social movements. But left on its own it is just as likely to collapse back into the [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Rabbit</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1661</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbit]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 06:50:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1661</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&quot;The aim must be to make the mass its own analyst, to spread the potential for leadership across the whole of the collective body.&quot;

Dead on. I just happened to be looking for some analysis of how ideas/movements are born, spread, and evolve, and here it is! Thank you. You guys are amazing.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;The aim must be to make the mass its own analyst, to spread the potential for leadership across the whole of the collective body.&#8221;</p>
<p>Dead on. I just happened to be looking for some analysis of how ideas/movements are born, spread, and evolve, and here it is! Thank you. You guys are amazing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Ian Bone</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1659</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Bone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2011 07:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1659</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Besides his well documented interest in corn circles Reg Presley (Troggs) has also invented a fog dispersal machine currently in operation at British airports.I once saw Reg in Andover in the morning and Dave Dee in Salisbury in the afternoon.Life is good sometimes.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Besides his well documented interest in corn circles Reg Presley (Troggs) has also invented a fog dispersal machine currently in operation at British airports.I once saw Reg in Andover in the morning and Dave Dee in Salisbury in the afternoon.Life is good sometimes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Beautiful Transgressions: After the Event? &#8211; Ceasefire Magazine</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1658</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Beautiful Transgressions: After the Event? &#8211; Ceasefire Magazine]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 08:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1658</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[[...] this incident was the element of change – the fairy dust- in the situation that resonated with people’s desires and experiences and enabled isolated acts [...]]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] this incident was the element of change – the fairy dust- in the situation that resonated with people’s desires and experiences and enabled isolated acts [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Keir</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1636</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Keir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 15:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1636</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dermot/Brian, yeah that&#039;s useful. I hadn&#039;t thought it but I suppose talking about fairy dust is, in part, a way to sidestep the spontaneity/organisation debate. As concepts tend to become saturated with meaning and turn into wooden words (as the Italians say) then perhaps each generation has to find its own way to restate these problems (find some sense in the nonsense). If that involves a little anecdote about swearing pop stars then all the better.

Pete, I actually have to do a little presentation to Stengers in some workshops in a couple of weeks. No doubt I&#039;ll end up talking about fairy dust and get laughed out of the room but I&#039;ll put the point you make about the normative uses made of complexity/chaos theory to her and report back.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dermot/Brian, yeah that&#8217;s useful. I hadn&#8217;t thought it but I suppose talking about fairy dust is, in part, a way to sidestep the spontaneity/organisation debate. As concepts tend to become saturated with meaning and turn into wooden words (as the Italians say) then perhaps each generation has to find its own way to restate these problems (find some sense in the nonsense). If that involves a little anecdote about swearing pop stars then all the better.</p>
<p>Pete, I actually have to do a little presentation to Stengers in some workshops in a couple of weeks. No doubt I&#8217;ll end up talking about fairy dust and get laughed out of the room but I&#8217;ll put the point you make about the normative uses made of complexity/chaos theory to her and report back.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: brian</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1635</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[brian]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2011 20:19:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1635</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dermot, that&#039;s a really interesting quote (especially Mattick’s claim that “the political mind of the radical is destined to be miserable”!)

The spontaneity vs organisation debate is often played out in a really sterile way: I can remember anarcho-syndicalists back in the 1980s deriding ultra-leftists for believing “it’ll be alright on the night” (when of course they should have been building rank-and-file workers’ groups). And the ultra-leftist critique was just as bitchy.

It’s probably more useful to think of spontaneity/‘organisation’ as two poles around which we shape ideas and practices of organising — even the most ‘spontaneous’ action has a hidden history, just as formal organisations have to break free of their structures. So maybe we should talk about organising (a verb) rather than organisation (a thing). Organising can take many forms, some permanent, some more temporary. And there can be movement between those two poles tactically as well as strategically.

Perhaps this sterile opposition between two modes of organising is itself bound up with a particular period of capitalist development, and therefore a particular period of workers’ self-organisation. With the partial collapse of neoliberalism (and bearing in mind the whole immaterial labour debate), perhaps we need to develop new, more fluid forms of politics appropriate to our times.

Of course it’s also possible that I am a mystic, with the secretly-held thought that I am talking nonsense… ;-)]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dermot, that&#8217;s a really interesting quote (especially Mattick’s claim that “the political mind of the radical is destined to be miserable”!)</p>
<p>The spontaneity vs organisation debate is often played out in a really sterile way: I can remember anarcho-syndicalists back in the 1980s deriding ultra-leftists for believing “it’ll be alright on the night” (when of course they should have been building rank-and-file workers’ groups). And the ultra-leftist critique was just as bitchy.</p>
<p>It’s probably more useful to think of spontaneity/‘organisation’ as two poles around which we shape ideas and practices of organising — even the most ‘spontaneous’ action has a hidden history, just as formal organisations have to break free of their structures. So maybe we should talk about organising (a verb) rather than organisation (a thing). Organising can take many forms, some permanent, some more temporary. And there can be movement between those two poles tactically as well as strategically.</p>
<p>Perhaps this sterile opposition between two modes of organising is itself bound up with a particular period of capitalist development, and therefore a particular period of workers’ self-organisation. With the partial collapse of neoliberalism (and bearing in mind the whole immaterial labour debate), perhaps we need to develop new, more fluid forms of politics appropriate to our times.</p>
<p>Of course it’s also possible that I am a mystic, with the secretly-held thought that I am talking nonsense… 😉</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Dermot</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1633</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dermot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2011 20:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1633</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[True enough Keir.

Needing to hold onto this idea of fairy dust i went away thinking and only later did it occur that similar discussions were had in the olde-worlde by the council communists in the 20s and 30s. 

Paul Mattick had this to say on the matter; which, if you replace &#039;spontenaity&#039; with &#039;fairy dust&#039; (and you can wade thru the painfully opaque phraseology in places) could still be relevant to this discussion!:

&quot;In the matter of organisation this, then is the dilemma of the radical: in order to do something of social significance, actions must be organised. Organised actions, however, turn into capitalistic channels. It seems that in order to do something now, one can do only the wrong thing and in order to avoid false steps, one should undertake none at all. The political mind of the radical is destined to be miserable; it is aware of its utopianism and it experiences nothing but failures. In mere self-defence, the radical stresses spontaneity always, unless he is a mystic, with the secretly-held thought that he is talking nonsense. But his persistence seems to prove that he never ceases to see some sense in the nonsense. 

Taking refuge in the idea of spontaneity is indicative of an actual or imagined inability to form effective organisations and a refusal to fight existing organisations in a &#039;realistic&#039; manner. For to fight them successfully would necessitate the formation of counter-organisations , which, by themselves, would defeat the reason for their existence. &#039;Spontaneity&#039; is thus a negative approach to the problem of social change and only in a purely ideological sense may it also be considered positive as it involves a mental divorce from those activities that favour the prevailing society. It sharpens critical faculty and leads to disassociation from futile activities and hopeless organisations. It looks for indications of social disintegration and for the limitations of class control. It results in a sharper distinction between appearance and reality and is, in brief, the trade mark of a revolutionary attitude. Since it is clear that some social forces, relations and organisations tend to disappear and others tend to take hold, those interested in the future, in the new forces in the making, will emphasise spontaneity; those more intimately connected with the old ones will stress the need for organisation.&quot;]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>True enough Keir.</p>
<p>Needing to hold onto this idea of fairy dust i went away thinking and only later did it occur that similar discussions were had in the olde-worlde by the council communists in the 20s and 30s. </p>
<p>Paul Mattick had this to say on the matter; which, if you replace &#8216;spontenaity&#8217; with &#8216;fairy dust&#8217; (and you can wade thru the painfully opaque phraseology in places) could still be relevant to this discussion!:</p>
<p>&#8220;In the matter of organisation this, then is the dilemma of the radical: in order to do something of social significance, actions must be organised. Organised actions, however, turn into capitalistic channels. It seems that in order to do something now, one can do only the wrong thing and in order to avoid false steps, one should undertake none at all. The political mind of the radical is destined to be miserable; it is aware of its utopianism and it experiences nothing but failures. In mere self-defence, the radical stresses spontaneity always, unless he is a mystic, with the secretly-held thought that he is talking nonsense. But his persistence seems to prove that he never ceases to see some sense in the nonsense. </p>
<p>Taking refuge in the idea of spontaneity is indicative of an actual or imagined inability to form effective organisations and a refusal to fight existing organisations in a &#8216;realistic&#8217; manner. For to fight them successfully would necessitate the formation of counter-organisations , which, by themselves, would defeat the reason for their existence. &#8216;Spontaneity&#8217; is thus a negative approach to the problem of social change and only in a purely ideological sense may it also be considered positive as it involves a mental divorce from those activities that favour the prevailing society. It sharpens critical faculty and leads to disassociation from futile activities and hopeless organisations. It looks for indications of social disintegration and for the limitations of class control. It results in a sharper distinction between appearance and reality and is, in brief, the trade mark of a revolutionary attitude. Since it is clear that some social forces, relations and organisations tend to disappear and others tend to take hold, those interested in the future, in the new forces in the making, will emphasise spontaneity; those more intimately connected with the old ones will stress the need for organisation.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: David</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1630</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 20:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1630</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We can take a little more insight from the Troggs. I had another listen to their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rzHpGjvRgTc&amp;NR=1&amp;feature=fvwp&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&quot;I Can&#039;t Control Myself&lt;/a&gt;&quot;. They&#039;re singing about a girl, but the song could easily be about how it feels to be in a moment of excess. The best line may well be: &quot;this kind of feeling could move a nation&quot;. Exactly! Though, when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6TywsL48Ww&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Buzzcocks covered the song&lt;/a&gt; a decade later, Howard Devoto replaced it with: &quot;this kind of feeling could DESTROY a nation&quot;, which is perfect.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We can take a little more insight from the Troggs. I had another listen to their <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rzHpGjvRgTc&#038;NR=1&#038;feature=fvwp" rel="nofollow">&#8220;I Can&#8217;t Control Myself</a>&#8220;. They&#8217;re singing about a girl, but the song could easily be about how it feels to be in a moment of excess. The best line may well be: &#8220;this kind of feeling could move a nation&#8221;. Exactly! Though, when <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6TywsL48Ww" rel="nofollow">Buzzcocks covered the song</a> a decade later, Howard Devoto replaced it with: &#8220;this kind of feeling could DESTROY a nation&#8221;, which is perfect.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Pete</title>
		<link>/2011/04/on-the-uses-of-fairy-dust/#comment-1629</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pete]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 16:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=674#comment-1629</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#039;d say that the naturalisation of ideology or the reification of the abstract as one commentator called it is as old as the enlightenment. Certainly The Origin of Species was picked up by both left and right as &#039;proof&#039; for their own ideologies. With the ideology of capitalism what we have is a political movement couched as a set of pragmatic inevitabilities; &quot;the way the world works&quot;.
It&#039;s a good move. The consumer does not associate capitalism with ideology, but with a gradual social and cultural evolution, a kind of capitalist teleology. The question then is not one of change but one of reform. To talk about change is to confront the way things are (nature) with the way things should be (ideal), and whilst we may like ideals we &#039;know&#039; that nature will ultimately dictate the things truly are.
Opposition to capitalism is always wrong- footed because it tries to play the same game, namely competing for the &#039;right by nature&#039; space. The last century has seen a whole bunch of disciplines clamour to be more scientific and so prove their natural worth. This to my mind is a fools errand resulting in dubious &#039;laws&#039; being generated to assert the scientific credentials of a discipline. It means that arguments too often hinge upon the natural/unnatural debate rather than being discussed around ideology and philosophy. Indeed ideology has become a dirty word, or at best a quaint old way of thinking before we had laws of economics, laws of the market so on and so forth.
The scientific method is a good tool, but it is not some kind of epistemological panacea, the totality of knowledge cannot be presented as an experimental model to be measured and impartially assessed (in fact science does not even work like that). Unfortunately Prigogine and Stengers are inclined to fall into this trap by saying (very roughly sketched) that chaos theory, maths and the natural world all show X therefore society will gravitate towards or *should* gravitate towards X. There is no reason to suppose that society operates in the same way as fluid dynamics (the primary use of chaos theory) or quantum theory or any other theory designed for other systems. Capitalism is an ideology and that is where it must be relocated and discussed. To rephrase an old slogan; &quot;Keep your method out my ideology&quot;.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;d say that the naturalisation of ideology or the reification of the abstract as one commentator called it is as old as the enlightenment. Certainly The Origin of Species was picked up by both left and right as &#8216;proof&#8217; for their own ideologies. With the ideology of capitalism what we have is a political movement couched as a set of pragmatic inevitabilities; &#8220;the way the world works&#8221;.<br />
It&#8217;s a good move. The consumer does not associate capitalism with ideology, but with a gradual social and cultural evolution, a kind of capitalist teleology. The question then is not one of change but one of reform. To talk about change is to confront the way things are (nature) with the way things should be (ideal), and whilst we may like ideals we &#8216;know&#8217; that nature will ultimately dictate the things truly are.<br />
Opposition to capitalism is always wrong- footed because it tries to play the same game, namely competing for the &#8216;right by nature&#8217; space. The last century has seen a whole bunch of disciplines clamour to be more scientific and so prove their natural worth. This to my mind is a fools errand resulting in dubious &#8216;laws&#8217; being generated to assert the scientific credentials of a discipline. It means that arguments too often hinge upon the natural/unnatural debate rather than being discussed around ideology and philosophy. Indeed ideology has become a dirty word, or at best a quaint old way of thinking before we had laws of economics, laws of the market so on and so forth.<br />
The scientific method is a good tool, but it is not some kind of epistemological panacea, the totality of knowledge cannot be presented as an experimental model to be measured and impartially assessed (in fact science does not even work like that). Unfortunately Prigogine and Stengers are inclined to fall into this trap by saying (very roughly sketched) that chaos theory, maths and the natural world all show X therefore society will gravitate towards or *should* gravitate towards X. There is no reason to suppose that society operates in the same way as fluid dynamics (the primary use of chaos theory) or quantum theory or any other theory designed for other systems. Capitalism is an ideology and that is where it must be relocated and discussed. To rephrase an old slogan; &#8220;Keep your method out my ideology&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
