<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: We mean it, maaan!</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/freelyassociating/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/</link>
	<description>THE FREE ASSOCIATION</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 11:17:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: Shaun May</title>
		<link>/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/#comment-6905</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shaun May]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 16:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=1996#comment-6905</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Anti-capitalist movements
December 2001 Originally commissioned for a book on ‘anti-capitalism’, the book’s editor decided that it was “too militant, not academic enough” (amongst other failings) and chose not to use it. It was published on The Commoner website, December 2001. 

Any text which takes an openly &#039;revolutionary critical&#039; approach (Marx : &#039;Practical criticism&#039; and does not take and locate the world &quot;in the form of the object&quot; but takes it &quot;subjectively, as sensuous human practice&quot; -Theses on Feuerbach) is always rejected by most commercial publishers. It is not &quot;academic enough&quot; because &#039;revolutionary critique&#039; grasps social development in terms of a conception which actively engages what is happening now as capital&#039;s crisis unfolds in order to &#039;revolutionise&#039; this world of capital. This is why these wretched publishing businesses will publish some of the dreariest, driest, loftily-detached and most tedious publications because they think they might find a market in the universities, students, etc. It is also why many &quot;Marxists&quot; (especially those with position in academia) compromise and &quot;academicise&quot; their work in order for it to be acceptable for publication. Whilst the most important texts tend to remain unpublished. The German Ideology was not fully published until 1932. Marx and Engels eventually &quot;left it to the gnawing criticism of the mice&quot; in some publishing office somewhere in Germany.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Anti-capitalist movements<br />
December 2001 Originally commissioned for a book on ‘anti-capitalism’, the book’s editor decided that it was “too militant, not academic enough” (amongst other failings) and chose not to use it. It was published on The Commoner website, December 2001. </p>
<p>Any text which takes an openly &#8216;revolutionary critical&#8217; approach (Marx : &#8216;Practical criticism&#8217; and does not take and locate the world &#8220;in the form of the object&#8221; but takes it &#8220;subjectively, as sensuous human practice&#8221; -Theses on Feuerbach) is always rejected by most commercial publishers. It is not &#8220;academic enough&#8221; because &#8216;revolutionary critique&#8217; grasps social development in terms of a conception which actively engages what is happening now as capital&#8217;s crisis unfolds in order to &#8216;revolutionise&#8217; this world of capital. This is why these wretched publishing businesses will publish some of the dreariest, driest, loftily-detached and most tedious publications because they think they might find a market in the universities, students, etc. It is also why many &#8220;Marxists&#8221; (especially those with position in academia) compromise and &#8220;academicise&#8221; their work in order for it to be acceptable for publication. Whilst the most important texts tend to remain unpublished. The German Ideology was not fully published until 1932. Marx and Engels eventually &#8220;left it to the gnawing criticism of the mice&#8221; in some publishing office somewhere in Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: brian</title>
		<link>/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/#comment-6900</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[brian]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 13:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=1996#comment-6900</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Keir: That’s really helpful on the tricky relationship between sincerity and artifice (the latter’s a more useful term than “inauthenticity”). I was trying to get back to it via the idea of autobiographical fiction but ran out of steam. Karl Ove Knausgaard’s ‘My Struggle’ is an epic shaggy dog tale which recounts the writer’s life in mind-numbingly boring detail. Part autobiography, part fiction, it’s less interested in the truth of the events it describes than in evoking feelings of brutal honesty. Knausgaard says in the third volume that memory is “sly and artful” and perhaps this is a key. You can question the veracity of almost every single detail in those books (did he really switch the bag from his left hand to his right? did he really play the Doors tape at that point?) – and members of his family have questioned far more than mere details – but the artifice of his writing is part of a wider truth process. And you’re right about earnestness which always seems to end up like &lt;a href=&quot;http://freelyassociating.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/rik-mayall.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or worse.

Simon: Erk, don’t ask me about Nietzsche, I’m really just &lt;a href=&quot;http://freelyassociating.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/i-have-no-idea.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;winging it here&lt;/a&gt; ;-). I’m not sure that the default position of cynicism is based on uncertainty (“which way should I commit?”). I think it’s more of a defence mechanism in the face of the deterritorialisng effect of capital. When all that is solid melts into air, only a fool would try to hang on to something (which is why trade unionists, radicals, feminists etc are always castigated as stick-in-the-muds resistant to change). It’d be easy in the face of this onslaught to say that we should hold fast to our positions, like unreconstructed tankies defending the Soviet Union, but I like your notion that sincerity is “the self-conscious, open construction of new truths”.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Keir: That’s really helpful on the tricky relationship between sincerity and artifice (the latter’s a more useful term than “inauthenticity”). I was trying to get back to it via the idea of autobiographical fiction but ran out of steam. Karl Ove Knausgaard’s ‘My Struggle’ is an epic shaggy dog tale which recounts the writer’s life in mind-numbingly boring detail. Part autobiography, part fiction, it’s less interested in the truth of the events it describes than in evoking feelings of brutal honesty. Knausgaard says in the third volume that memory is “sly and artful” and perhaps this is a key. You can question the veracity of almost every single detail in those books (did he really switch the bag from his left hand to his right? did he really play the Doors tape at that point?) – and members of his family have questioned far more than mere details – but the artifice of his writing is part of a wider truth process. And you’re right about earnestness which always seems to end up like <a href="http://freelyassociating.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/rik-mayall.jpg" rel="nofollow">this</a> or worse.</p>
<p>Simon: Erk, don’t ask me about Nietzsche, I’m really just <a href="http://freelyassociating.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/i-have-no-idea.jpg" rel="nofollow">winging it here</a> ;-). I’m not sure that the default position of cynicism is based on uncertainty (“which way should I commit?”). I think it’s more of a defence mechanism in the face of the deterritorialisng effect of capital. When all that is solid melts into air, only a fool would try to hang on to something (which is why trade unionists, radicals, feminists etc are always castigated as stick-in-the-muds resistant to change). It’d be easy in the face of this onslaught to say that we should hold fast to our positions, like unreconstructed tankies defending the Soviet Union, but I like your notion that sincerity is “the self-conscious, open construction of new truths”.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Simon Thorpe</title>
		<link>/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/#comment-6899</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon Thorpe]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2015 11:27:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=1996#comment-6899</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is really interesting - thank you! Let me try to get it straight...

When you were saying &#039;lazy cynicism ... makes sincere statements of belief both hard to express and difficult to take seriously&#039;, I was screaming inside - what about Nietzsche?! Are you saying scepticism of belief and conviction is a bad thing? Surely beliefs ARE always wrong; like knowledge, except even worse.

And then you bring Nietzsche in at the end (though I don&#039;t quite get the quote) and elaborate more on sincerity, and I wonder if we&#039;re actually on the same page. Could I successfully extrapolate that this idea of sincerity, then, as it&#039;s &#039;not about authenticity or truth&#039;, is in part the self-conscious, open construction of new truths (or truth procedures)? A way of moving forward through the (necessary) fog of uncertainty.

Because surely you&#039;re not implying that the uncertainty at the root of our cynicism is just a false consciousness, ideology? To my mind this impossibility of knowledge is the only - or the most - reliable outcome of the history of knowledge.

But maybe I&#039;m too readily conflating knowledge and belief?

Anyway, I think I like this idea of sincerity. Want to know more!

Ah there&#039;s more! Will read this next: http://freelyassociating.org/2015/02/on-explosions-of-sincerity/]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is really interesting &#8211; thank you! Let me try to get it straight&#8230;</p>
<p>When you were saying &#8216;lazy cynicism &#8230; makes sincere statements of belief both hard to express and difficult to take seriously&#8217;, I was screaming inside &#8211; what about Nietzsche?! Are you saying scepticism of belief and conviction is a bad thing? Surely beliefs ARE always wrong; like knowledge, except even worse.</p>
<p>And then you bring Nietzsche in at the end (though I don&#8217;t quite get the quote) and elaborate more on sincerity, and I wonder if we&#8217;re actually on the same page. Could I successfully extrapolate that this idea of sincerity, then, as it&#8217;s &#8216;not about authenticity or truth&#8217;, is in part the self-conscious, open construction of new truths (or truth procedures)? A way of moving forward through the (necessary) fog of uncertainty.</p>
<p>Because surely you&#8217;re not implying that the uncertainty at the root of our cynicism is just a false consciousness, ideology? To my mind this impossibility of knowledge is the only &#8211; or the most &#8211; reliable outcome of the history of knowledge.</p>
<p>But maybe I&#8217;m too readily conflating knowledge and belief?</p>
<p>Anyway, I think I like this idea of sincerity. Want to know more!</p>
<p>Ah there&#8217;s more! Will read this next: <a href="http://freelyassociating.org/2015/02/on-explosions-of-sincerity/" rel="nofollow">http://freelyassociating.org/2015/02/on-explosions-of-sincerity/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: keir</title>
		<link>/2015/06/we-mean-it-maaan/#comment-6898</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[keir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 19:17:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://freelyassociating.org/?p=1996#comment-6898</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Great post Brian. I’ve been thinking about a similar problem recently, trying to resolve our apparent demand for anti-ironic sincerity with other more playful strategies we’ve suggested in the past, such as using Ziggy Stardust to rethink charismatic political leadership. We were attracted to the later precisely because the character was based on a kind of open inauthenticity with the hope that this model might allow us access to the focal point of charismatic leadership without the risks of identifying this point with any specific individual. This binary of authenticity and artifice runs right through pop culture and its popular modernist wing. I also think it’s significant that the Ziggy character is presented as arriving from an alien world. This allows him to break with the sense of present society and highlight the alienation felt by many. There’s a persistent theme of alien futurism in pop. Just think of the AfroFuturism of George Clinton or Lee ‘Scratch’ Perry or even the ‘whiter than white’ avant-techno modernism of Kraftwerk or even Gary Numan (the Tory twat). So how can you meld a demand for sincerity with a strategy of alien artifice? Well separating sincerity from authenticity would help. Can you be sincerely inauthentic? Yes I think so. But we might want to protect a certain sense of camp as well. I’m not sure but Novaramedia were discussing Fully Automated Luxury Communism on their radio show today. At a certain point @AyoCaesar reminded everyone that there is a certain campness to the slogan which makes it attractive.

Perhaps one way into this is to remember that there is an original and helpful use of irony which employs it as a ground clearing operation. Or as David Foster Wallace says,“a critical negation that would make it self-evident to everyone that the world is not as it seems.” The problems come when irony becomes all-pervasive, preventing any sincere statement of belief from being taken seriously. Perhaps then “explosions of sincerity” should be thought of the same way; as ground clearing exercises from which we can reinsert trace levels of camp and irony to deflate the risk of pomposity and earnestness.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Great post Brian. I’ve been thinking about a similar problem recently, trying to resolve our apparent demand for anti-ironic sincerity with other more playful strategies we’ve suggested in the past, such as using Ziggy Stardust to rethink charismatic political leadership. We were attracted to the later precisely because the character was based on a kind of open inauthenticity with the hope that this model might allow us access to the focal point of charismatic leadership without the risks of identifying this point with any specific individual. This binary of authenticity and artifice runs right through pop culture and its popular modernist wing. I also think it’s significant that the Ziggy character is presented as arriving from an alien world. This allows him to break with the sense of present society and highlight the alienation felt by many. There’s a persistent theme of alien futurism in pop. Just think of the AfroFuturism of George Clinton or Lee ‘Scratch’ Perry or even the ‘whiter than white’ avant-techno modernism of Kraftwerk or even Gary Numan (the Tory twat). So how can you meld a demand for sincerity with a strategy of alien artifice? Well separating sincerity from authenticity would help. Can you be sincerely inauthentic? Yes I think so. But we might want to protect a certain sense of camp as well. I’m not sure but Novaramedia were discussing Fully Automated Luxury Communism on their radio show today. At a certain point @AyoCaesar reminded everyone that there is a certain campness to the slogan which makes it attractive.</p>
<p>Perhaps one way into this is to remember that there is an original and helpful use of irony which employs it as a ground clearing operation. Or as David Foster Wallace says,“a critical negation that would make it self-evident to everyone that the world is not as it seems.” The problems come when irony becomes all-pervasive, preventing any sincere statement of belief from being taken seriously. Perhaps then “explosions of sincerity” should be thought of the same way; as ground clearing exercises from which we can reinsert trace levels of camp and irony to deflate the risk of pomposity and earnestness.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
